<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A brief treatise of the vse of the globe celestiall and terrestriall wherein is set downe the principles of the mathematicks, fit for all trauellers, nauigators, and all others that doe loue the knowledge of the same art. By R. T.</title>
            <author>R. T. (Robert Tanner)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1616</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 52 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13364</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23672</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113521</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848755</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848755</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13868</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13364)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13868)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1695:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A brief treatise of the vse of the globe celestiall and terrestriall wherein is set downe the principles of the mathematicks, fit for all trauellers, nauigators, and all others that doe loue the knowledge of the same art. By R. T.</title>
                  <author>R. T. (Robert Tanner)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 56 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by Felix Kyngston, for Thomas Man,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1616.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Astronomy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13868:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13868:1"/>
            <p>A BRIEF TREATISE OF THE VSE OF THE Globe Celeſtiall and Terreſtriall:</p>
            <p>WHEREIN IS SET DOWNE the principles of the Mathematicks, fit for all trauellers, Nauigators, and all others that doe loue the knowledge of the ſame Art.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> R. T.</p>
            <p>AT LONDON Imprinted by FELIX KYNGSTON, for <hi>Thomas Man.</hi> 1616.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:13868:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13868:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE TO the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
               </hi> Doe here preſent thee (gentle Reader) with a briefe colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the vſe of the Globe, which may ſerue for an intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction to young Students in the Mathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matikes, requiring thee to accept thereof: for I doubt not it will be very good for the furtherance of trauellers in the Art of Nauigation: and to all others that are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous of the knowledge of the beautifull frame of the celeſtiall Orbs, with their quantities, diſtances, courſes, and maruei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous motions of the Globes of the Sunne, Moone, Planets and fixed ſtarres. If there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this my labour ſhall be gratefully ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, as I doubt not but it ſhall, if thou pleaſe iuſtly to cenſure thereof: I ſhall be incouraged hereafter to ſet foorth a worke
<pb facs="tcp:13868:3"/>
of more worth: ſo I referre my ſelfe to your fauourable iudgements and curteſies, committing thee to the ſacred tuition of him that ruleth all. Farewell.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in all affection, <hi>R. T.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:13868:3"/>
            <head>INTRODV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CTION TO Aſtronomy.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Definitions of the Globe.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Globe is a perfect round bodie, contained vnder one plaine: in the middle thereof there is a poynt called the Ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, from whence all lines drawne to the outſide are of like length, and called Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diameters.</p>
               <p>The axes of the Globe is a diameter, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout which it moueth; and the ends there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of are called the poles of the Globe.</p>
               <p>In this reſpect the frame of the heauens is called the Globe of the heauens, and the earth his Center.</p>
               <p>The axes is a line imagined, paſſing by
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:13868:4"/>
the Center of the earth to the heauens, and the ends thereof is called the poles, which are two points imagined in the heauens, whereof the one is called the North pole, and the other the South pole.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Circles of the Globe.</head>
               <p>Circles of the Globe are certaine ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginarie lines, and are termed either leſſer, or greater Circles.</p>
               <p>Greater Circles are ſuch as diuideth the Globe into two equall parts.</p>
               <p>Leſſer are ſuch as diuide the Globe into vnequall parts.</p>
               <p>Greater Circles of the Globe in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon account are ſixe in number, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <head>The</head>
                  <item>Horizon.</item>
                  <item>Meridian.</item>
                  <item>Equinoctiall.</item>
                  <item>Zodiake.</item>
                  <item>Two Collures.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Leſſer Circles in common account are foure in number, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <head>The</head>
                  <item>Two Tropicks.</item>
                  <item>Two poler Circles.</item>
               </list>
               <p>The Horizon diuideth that part of the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:13868:4"/>
heauens we doe ſee, from that part wee ſee not, and is that Circle, where ſtanding in a plaine field, and looking about, you would imagine the earth and heauens doe meete together, and cannot be perfectly diſcerned but at ſea.</p>
               <p>The axes of the Horizon, is an imagined line, paſſing by the Center of the earth to the heauens, and the ends thereof, are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the poles <hi>Zenith</hi> and <hi>Nadir.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Zenith</hi> is the point direct ouer our heads, and the <hi>Nadir</hi> direct vnder our feet.</p>
               <p>As a man moueth himſelfe any way, ſo is altered the Horizon.</p>
               <p>The Meridian cutteth the Horizon at right ſphericall angles, and paſſeth by the poles of heauen, and by the <hi>Zenith</hi> and <hi>Nadir,</hi> and is that Circle wherein the ☉ is at noone, and at midnight: it diuideth the Globe into two equall parts by Eaſt and Weſt, whoſe axes is a line paſſing by the Center of the earth to the heauens, and the ends thereof the poles, which are the two points of the interſection of the Eaſt and Weſt.</p>
               <p>Any many mouing directly North and South, keepeth the ſame Meridian: but go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Eaſt or Weſt, he altereth the ſame.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:13868:5"/>
The Equinoctiall cutteth the Meridian at right ſphericall angles, and lieth equidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant betwixt each poles, and diuideth the Globe into two equall parts, by North and South parts, to which Circle when the ☉ commeth vnder it, it maketh the day and night of like length to all people in the world, except vnder the poles, and the ☉ commeth vnder this Circle two daies in the yeere, <hi>viz.</hi> the 11. of March, and on the 14. of September.</p>
               <p>The axes and poles whereof are the axes and poles of heauen.</p>
               <p>The Zodiack is a great Circle, hauing in breadth twelue degrees, which breadth is limited for the wandring of planets, vpon which Circle are the twelue ſignes placed, which are twelue Conſtellations.</p>
               <p>A Conſtellation is any certaine number of ſtars, gathered together into one forme by the ancient Aſtronomers, who haue gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen them names, whereby they are knowne to all Chriſtendome: which ſignes haue certaine characters giuen vnto them, and are theſe following.</p>
               <list>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:13868:5"/>
                  <item>1 <hi>March.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2 <hi>Aprill.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3 <hi>May.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4 <hi>Iune.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>5 <hi>Iuly.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>6 <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Northen ſignes.</head>
                  <item>1 <hi>Aries.</hi> ♈</item>
                  <item>2 <hi>Taurus.</hi> ♉</item>
                  <item>3 <hi>Gemini.</hi> ♊</item>
                  <item>4 <hi>Cancer.</hi> ♋</item>
                  <item>5 <hi>Leo.</hi> ♌</item>
                  <item>6 <hi>Virgo.</hi> ♍</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <item>7 <hi>Septemb.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>8 <hi>October.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>9 <hi>Nouember.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>10 <hi>Decemb.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>11 <hi>Ianuary.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>12 <hi>February.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Southern ſignes.</head>
                  <item>7 <hi>Libra.</hi> ♎</item>
                  <item>8 <hi>Scorpio.</hi> ♏</item>
                  <item>9 <hi>Sagittarius.</hi> ♐</item>
                  <item>10 <hi>Capricornus</hi> ♑</item>
                  <item>11 <hi>Aquarius</hi> ♒</item>
                  <item>12 <hi>Piſces.</hi> ♓</item>
               </list>
               <p>The firſt ſixe are called Northen ſignes, for that they are placed vpon the North ſide of the equinoctiall; and the laſt ſixe are called Southerne ſignes, for that they are placed vpon the South ſide of the equino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiall.</p>
               <p>In the middle of the Zodiacke is a line called the ecliptick, from which line the Center of the ☉ neuer ſwarueth, and this line cutteth the equinoctiall at oblique angles, and ſwarueth from it 23 degrees 30 minutes: which line when the ☉ and <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> are in a diameter, that is, oppoſite, then is the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> eclipſed, that is, darkned by the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:13868:6"/>
of the earth, the earth being betwixt the ☉ and the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>.</p>
               <p>And when the ☉ and <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> are both vnder the line in a ſemidiamiter, then is the ☉ e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipſed, the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> being interpoſed betwixt our ſight and the ☉: this line eclipticke is deſcribed vpon the Globe for the whole Zodiack, whoſe axe is a line paſſing by the Center of the earth to the heauens, and the ends thereof are his poles, which are two points ſo farre diſtant from the poles of the world, as the ☉ his greateſt diſtance from the equinoctiall, <hi>viz.</hi> 23 degrees 30 min.</p>
               <p>The two Collures are two meridians cutting the equinoctiall, and the eclipticke into foure equall parts, the one paſsing by the firſt point of ♈ and ♎, and is called the equinoctiall Collure. The other paſsing by the firſt point of ♋ and ♑, and is called the ſolſtitiall Collure: theſe two Circles do di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide the yeere in foure equall parts, <hi>viz.</hi> Spring-time, Sommer, Harueſt, and Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
               <list>
                  <head>Spring-time.</head>
                  <item>1 ♈</item>
                  <item>2 ♉</item>
                  <item>3 ♊</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Sommer.</head>
                  <item>4 ♋</item>
                  <item>5 ♌</item>
                  <item>6 ♍</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:13868:6"/>
                  <head>Harueſt.</head>
                  <item>7 ♎</item>
                  <item>8 ♏</item>
                  <item>9 ♐</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Winter.</head>
                  <item>10 ♑</item>
                  <item>11 ♒</item>
                  <item>12 ♓</item>
               </list>
               <p>The meaning wherof is thus: From that time the ☉ entreth into ♈, till it enter into ♋, is called Spring-time, and ſo of the reſt, ſo that it is the paſſage of the ☉ in the ſignes, that cauſeth the alteration of ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and the ☉ paſſeth thoroughout the whole ſignes in one yeere, <hi>viz.</hi> in 365 daies and 6 houres neere.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the leſſer Circle.</head>
               <p>THe Tropick of ♋ is a Circle parallel to the equinoctiall 23 degrees 30 min. diſtant fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it, Northward, and is that Circle vnder which the Center of the ☉ maketh her diagonall arke, when ſhe is in the firſt point of ♋, which is to vs that haue Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Latitude, the longeſt day in the yeere being the 12 or 13 of Iune.</p>
               <p>The Tropick of ♑ is a Circle parallel to the equinoctiall, ſo farre to the Southward, as the Tropick of ♋ is Northward, <hi>viz.</hi> 23 degrees 30 min. and is that Circle vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which the Center of the ☉ maketh
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:13868:7"/>
her diagonall arke, when ſhe is in the firſt point of ♑, which to vs that haue Northen Latitude, is the ſhorteſt day in winter, <hi>viz.</hi> the 12. or 13. of December. Theſe two Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles are termed the limit of the ☉ pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe: for betweene theſe two Circles the ☉ hath his continuall courſe, and neuer ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth beyond any of them.</p>
               <p>The Circle articke is a Circle parallel to the equinoctiall, ſo farre diſtant from the North pole, as the tropicke of Cancer is from the equinoctial, <hi>viz.</hi> 23. degr. 30. min.</p>
               <p>The Circle antarticke is a Circle parallel to the equinoctiall ſo farre diſtant from the South pole, as the tropick of ♑ is from the equinoctiall, <hi>viz.</hi> 23. degr. 30. min.</p>
               <p>Now you muſt vnderſtand, there is but one Equinoctiall, one Zodiacke, one Eclip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick, two Collures.</p>
               <p>But there are diuers Meridians, al which meete in the two poles of the world, and cut the equinoctiall at right angles, and are ſo many in number as there can be points imagined in the equinoctiall.</p>
               <p>There are diuers Horizons: for the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizon altereth to any man, according as he moueth himſelfe from his place of being.</p>
               <p>There are diuers Parallels, ſo called for
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:13868:7"/>
that they are parallel to the equinoctiall, and are ſo many in number, as there can be points imagined in the Meridian.</p>
               <p>Beſides theſe Circles, before mentioned, there are foure other kinde of Circles of great vſe, <hi>viz.</hi> Azimoth and Almicanthars, Circles of Longitude and Latitude.</p>
               <p>Azimoths are great Circles, and meete all in the Zenith, and Nadir, and cut the Horizon at right angles, and are numbred in the Horizon.</p>
               <p>Almicanthars are leſſer Circles parallel to the Horizon, as the parallels are to the equinoctiall, and are numbred from the Horizon towards the Zenith.</p>
               <p>Circles of Longitude are great Circles, meeting all in the poles of the Eclipticke, and cut the Eclipticke at right angles, and are numbred in the Ecliptick.</p>
               <p>Circles of Latitude are leſſer Circles pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel to the Ecliptick, as the parallels are to the equinoctiall, and are numbred from the Eclipticke, to the poles of the Eclip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke.</p>
               <p>Euery Circle of the Globe is imagined to be diuided into 360 degrees, and euery degree into 60. minutes, euery minute into 60 ſeconds, and ſo tell the tenth for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſenes,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:13868:8"/>
for that a degree in the heauens is a large ſpace.</p>
               <p>In euery great Circle the degrees are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall one to another.</p>
               <p>In euery leſſer Circle they are equall in the ſame Circle, but vnequall to thoſe of another Circle, according as they grow neerer the poles.</p>
               <p>There belongeth to the furniſhing of a Globe two other things, that is, an houre Circle, with Index and a quadrant of Alti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude.</p>
               <p>The houre Circle is of braſſe, diuided in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to 24. houres by twice 12, and is to be pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced vpon the Meridian, vpon the pole ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uated parallel to the equinoctiall.</p>
               <p>The Index is a little ruler to be put vpon the pole.</p>
               <p>The quadrant of Altitude is a bowed ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of braſſe, diuided into 60. degrees, equal to the degrees of the Globe, and hath a ioint to faſten the ſame vpon the Meridian, and is alwaies to be placed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Zenith.</p>
               <p>For the practiſe of Aſtronomie &amp; Coſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mographie, there are two Globes made, the one of the Heauens, which is called the Celeſtiall globe, and the other of the Earth, which is called the Terreſtriall globe.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:13868:8"/>
Vpon the Celeſtiall Globe are pictured al the ſtarres vpon the Conuexitie thereof, as wee behold them in the heauens, in the Concauitie there of in forme and diſtance.</p>
               <p>Vpon the Globe of the earth is ſet ſea and land, making one perfect body, all the knowne parts being laid downe in forme, proportion, and diſtance by ſcale, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the proportion of the earth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the ſuperficies of the Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiall Globe.</head>
               <p>TO the intent that the knowledge of ſtarres might bee brought in rule and memorie of men, therefore the ancient A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtronomers gathered them together into certaine conſtellations, and gaue them names, whereby they are knowne vnto all the world, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> haue the knowledge of letters.</p>
               <p>A Conſtellation is a certaine number of ſtarres gathered together in one forme, and ſo retaine their names, whereby they are particularly knowne, and are in number, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ancient account, 48. and are diuided into three parts, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <item>Northen</item>
                  <item>Zodiake</item>
                  <item>Southerne</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Conſtellations</head>
                  <item>21</item>
                  <item>12</item>
                  <item>15</item>
               </list>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <p>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:13868:9"/>
Beſides theſe there are 120. ſtarres that are exempt out of all the Conſtellations, ſo that the number of ſtars ſet vpon the Globe are 1025, and diuers of them haue proper names, which I here omit.</p>
               <p>You muſt vnderſtand that all the ſtarres in heauen are not numbred, nor cannot, for that diuers of them are ſo ſmall, but theſe 2025 are the principalleſt amongſt them, and all that haue yet euer been accounted of.</p>
               <p>You muſt vnderſtand, that of theſe ſtars ſome are greater then other, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed in ſixe ſorts of b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gneſſes, and their meaſures is the earth, and their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portions are thus deliuered, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A ſtarre of the firſt bignes is 107. times bigger then the earth.</p>
               <p>A ſtarre of the ſecond bignes is 90. times the globe of the earth.</p>
               <p>A ſtarre of the third bignes is 72 times the globe of the earth.</p>
               <p>A ſtarre of the fourth bignes is 54 times the globe of the earth.</p>
               <p>A ſtarre of the fifth bignes is 36 times the globe of the earth.</p>
               <p>A ſtarre of the ſixth bignes is 18 times the globe of the earth.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:13868:9"/>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>15</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>45</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Stars mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitude,</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>and the quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titie of each magnitude.</cell>
                        <cell>208</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>474</cell>
                        <cell>In all 1025</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>427</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>49</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>Cloudie.</cell>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>Obſcure.</cell>
                        <cell>9</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>Parnaſſus fayre.</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>Vpon each Globe there is a table ſet downe in what forme euery ſtarre of any bignes is made, whereby you may readily know any ſtarre in any Conſtellation of what bignes it is.</p>
               <p>And thus much in briefe for the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perficies of the Globe of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens.</p>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <p>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:13868:10"/>
haue Sotherne Latitude that dwell on the South ſide of the equinoctiall.</p>
               <list>
                  <head>The earth is diuided into foure parts, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <item>Europa.</item>
                  <item>Aſia.</item>
                  <item>Africa.</item>
                  <item>America.</item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <hi>Europe</hi> is bounded from <hi>Aſia</hi> by the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land ſea, and <hi>Mary mauritane,</hi> by the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches called <hi>Palus meotis,</hi> and by the riuer <hi>Tanis</hi> and <hi>Dwiana.</hi>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <head>The Prouinces are theſe.</head>
                  <item>1 <hi>Germanie.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2 <hi>Italy.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3 <hi>France.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4 <hi>Spayne.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>5 <hi>Denmarke.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>6 <hi>Norway.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>7 <hi>Swedeland.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>8 <hi>Moſcouia.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>9 <hi>Polonia.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>10 <hi>Hungaria.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>11 <hi>Clauonia and</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>12 <hi>Grecia.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>The principall Ilands.</head>
                  <item>1 <hi>England.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2 <hi>Scotland.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3 <hi>Ireland.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4 <hi>Sicilia.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>5 <hi>Candia.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>6 <hi>Corſica.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>7 <hi>Sardigna.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>8 <hi>Negroponte.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aſia</hi> is bounded from <hi>Europe</hi> by the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer <hi>Tanis</hi> and <hi>Dwiana,</hi> from <hi>Afrieke</hi> by the narrow necke of Land betwixt the red ſea, and the mid-land ſea.</p>
               <list>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:13868:10"/>
                  <head>The Prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are</head>
                  <item>China.</item>
                  <item>Perſia.</item>
                  <item>Part of Moſcouia, and</item>
                  <item>Tartaria.</item>
               </list>
               <p>In this part of the world was Paradiſe and the Land of promiſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Africa</hi> is bounded with the mid-land ſea and the red ſea.</p>
               <list>
                  <head>Prouinces.</head>
                  <item>1 <hi>Egypt.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2 <hi>Barbaria.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3 <hi>Aethiopia.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4 <hi>Nubia.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>5 <hi>Abaſmies.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>6 <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>onomotopa.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Ilands.</head>
                  <item>1 <hi>Madagaſcat, or S. Lorreny<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2 <hi>S. Thome.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3 <hi>Inſule de Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po verde.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4 <hi>Inſule de Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naria.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>5 <hi>Inſule de Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dera.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <hi>America</hi> is wholly bounded by the Sea, and the ſtraight of <hi>Magellanus,</hi> and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth in two parts, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <item>Mexicana.</item>
                  <item>Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ana.</item>
               </list>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <div n="1" type="proposition">
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:13868:11"/>
                  <head>FIRST PROPOSITION OF the Celeſtiall Globe. <hi>The day of the moneth being giuen, to finde the place of the</hi> ☉.</head>
                  <p>VPon the Horizon of the Globe is graduated the theoricke of the ☉, that is, there is placed the moneth, and their daies, the ſignes and their degrees. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore finde the day of the moneth, and right againſt the ſame you ſhall finde the ſigne and degree that the ☉ poſſeſſeth.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="proposition">
                  <head>Propoſition 2. <hi>The place of the</hi> ☉ <hi>being giuen, to finde the day of the moneth.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>FInde the place of the ☉ in the Horizon, and againſt the ſame you ſhall finde the day of the moneth.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="proposition">
                  <head>Propoſition 3. <hi>The place of the</hi> ☉ <hi>being giuen, to finde the Declination.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>BRing the place of the ☉ to the Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian of the Globe, and the portion of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:13868:11"/>
the Meridian included betwixt the place of the ☉ and the equinoctiall, ſheweth the declination.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="proposition">
                  <head>Propoſition 4. <hi>The place of the</hi> ☉ <hi>and the Meridian height of the</hi> ☉ <hi>being giuen, to finde the height of the Pole.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>BRing the place of the ☉ to the Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian of the Globe, and from that point account downwards to the Horizon the height of the ☉, and let the ends there of end in the Horizon: then in the oppoſite part, you ſhall finde cut on the Meridian the height of the Pole, that is, the portion of the Meridian included betwixt the Pole and Horizon, ſheweth the height of the Pole.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="proposition">
                  <head>Propoſition 5. <hi>To rectifie the Globe fit for vſe, the eleuation of the Pole being knowne.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>SEt the poles anſwerable to the poles of Heauen.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="proposition">
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:13868:12"/>
                  <head>Propoſition 6. <hi>To rectifie the quadrant of altitude.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>SEt the ioynt thereof vpon the Meridian ſo farre diſtant from the equinoctiall, as the poles is eliuated aboue the Horizon, that is, place the ioynt in the Zenith.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="proposition">
                  <head>Propoſition 7. <hi>To rectifie the Index of the houre Circle, for any day appointed.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>BRing the place of the ☉ to the Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian of the Globe, and then put the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dex vpon 12 of the clocke, or vpon that 12, which is vppermoſt from the Horizon.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="proposition">
                  <head>Propoſition 8. <hi>The eleuation of the Pole and place of the</hi> ☉ <hi>being giuen, to finde the Meridian, height of the</hi> ☉.</head>
                  <p>THe Globe rectified, bring the place of the ☉ to the meridian, and the degrees from the place of the ☉ to the Horizon, ſheweth the demaund.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="proposition">
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:13868:12"/>
                  <head>Propoſition 9. <hi>The eleuation of the Pole and place of the</hi> ☉ <hi>being giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to find the houre of the</hi> ☉ <hi>riſing.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THe Globe and Index of the houre cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle being rectified, bring the place of the ☉ to the Eaſt ſide of the Horizon, and the Index of the houre circle ſheweth the houre of the ☉ riſing.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="proposition">
                  <head>Propoſition 10. <hi>The eleuation of the Pole and place of the</hi> ☉ <hi>being giuen, to finde the houre of the</hi> ☉ <hi>ſetting.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THe Globe and Index of the houre cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle being rectified, bring the place of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o the Weſt ſide of the Globe, and the Index of the houre circle ſheweth the houre of the ☉ ſetting.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="proposition">
                  <head>Propoſition 11. <hi>The eleuation of the Pole and place of the</hi> ☉ <hi>being giuen, to finde the length of the day.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>FInde the houre of ☉ ſetting by the laſt propoſition, and double that time, ſo haue you the length of the day.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="proposition">
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:13868:13"/>
                  <head>Propoſition 12. <hi>The eleuation of the Pole and place of the</hi> ☉ <hi>being giuen, to finde the Amplitude.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THe Globe rectified, bring the place of the ☉ to the Horizon, and the portion of the Horizon included betwixt the place of the ☉, and the point of Eaſt or Weſt, ſheweth the amplitude.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="proposition">
                  <head>Propoſition 13. <hi>The place of the</hi> ☉ <hi>and Amplitude being gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, to finde the height of the Pole.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>TVrne the Globe and moue the Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian vntill you haue fitted the place of the ☉ in the point of the Amplitude, and then the pole of the Globe ſheweth the height of the pole, that is, the place inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded betwixt the pole of the Globe and the Horizon, ſheweth in the Meridian the height thereof.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="proposition">
                  <head>Propoſition 14. <hi>The place of the</hi> ☉ <hi>being giuen, to finde the right aſcention thereof.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>BRing the place of the ☉ to the Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian, and the degree cut by the Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:13868:13"/>
in the Equinoctiall, ſheweth the right Aſcention.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="15" type="proposition">
                  <head>Propoſition 15. <hi>The eleuation of the Pole and place of the</hi> ☉ <hi>being giuen, to find the crooked Aſcention.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THe Globe rectified, bring the place of the ☉ to the Eaſt ſide of the Globe, and the degree cut by the Horizon in the equinoctial, ſheweth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> crooked Aſcention.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="16" type="proposition">
                  <head>Propoſition 16. <hi>To finde the difference of Aſcention.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>FIrſt finde the right, and then the croo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Aſcention: then take the leſſe from the greater, and that reſt ſheweth the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of Aſcention, except that remainer do exceed 180 degrees, and then that reſt ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from 360 degrees, ſheweth the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of Aſcention.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="17" type="proposition">
                  <head>Propoſition 17. <hi>By the difference of Aſcention, to finde the length of the day.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>DOuble the difference of Aſcention, &amp; reduce that into time, by allowing 15
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                        <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:13868:14"/>
turne the Globe, vntill the place of the ☉ touch the edge of the quadrant, then the Index of the houre Circle ſheweth the houre, and the degree cut on the quadrant of altitude, ſheweth the height of the ☉ at that time.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="22" type="proposition">
                  <head>Propoſition 22. <hi>The houre of the day being giuen, to finde the Azminth of the</hi> ☉.</head>
                  <p>ALL things rectified, turne the Index to the houre: then bring the quadrant of Altitude on the place of the ☉, and the end thereof in the Horizon ſheweth the Azminth.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:13868:14"/>
               <head>OF THE STARS.</head>
               <div n="1" type="proposition">
                  <head>Propoſition 1. <hi>To finde the Declination of any Starre.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>VVOrke by the Starre, as you did by the ☉ in the 3. Propoſition, <hi>viz.</hi> An example: <hi>Arcturus</hi> in <hi>Bootes leggs</hi> brought to the Meridian of the Globe, the portion of the Meridian betwixt the place and the equinoctiall, ſheweth his declina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to be Northerne.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="proposition">
                  <head>Propoſition 2. <hi>The meridian height of any ſtarre being giuen, to finde the height of the Pole.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>VVOrke by the ſtarre, as you did by the ☉ in the 4. Propoſition, <hi>viz. Arcturus meridional</hi> height ſuppoſed to be giuen 60 degr. then the height of the Pole oppoſite is found to be 52 degrees.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="proposition">
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:13868:15"/>
                  <head>Propoſition 3. <hi>To finde the houre of riſing of any ſtarre.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>AL things rectified, work by the ſtarre, as by the ☉ in the 9. Propoſition: for to know at any time the riſing of <hi>Arctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus,</hi> or any other*, you muſt know in what ſigne the ☉ is. As for example: The ☉ ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing in the 19 degree of ♑, which being brought vnder the fixed Meridian, and then the Globe and Index rectified, <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cturns</hi> is then found to riſe at 6 houres, and 30 minutes in the morning, and ſetteth in the euening at houre 10. 30 minutes.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="proposition">
                  <head>Propoſition 4. <hi>To finde the houre of any ſtarre ſetting.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>AL things rectified, work by the ſtarre, as by the ☉ in the 10 Propoſition, or precedent demonſtration.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="proposition">
                  <head>Propoſition 5. <hi>To finde the time of any ſtarre aboue the earth.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>FIrſt finde the houre of riſing, and then the houre of ſetting: the difference of
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:13868:15"/>
which time is the thing required.</p>
                  <div type="example">
                     <head>Example.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Arcturus</hi> is found by the former Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to riſe at houre 6. 30, which is 5. 30 before 12, and hee ſetteth at 10. 30: both which times added together, maketh 16 houres, and ſo is <hi>Arcturus</hi> found to be 16 houres aboue the earth.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="proposition">
                  <head>Propoſition 6. <hi>To finde the amplitude of any ſtarre.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>VVOrke as by the ☉ in the 12 Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition. Example: <hi>Arcturus</hi> am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plitude is found then, when he is brought to the Horizon; in the ſide is 37 degrees of Amplitude.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="proposition">
                  <head>Propoſition 7. <hi>The amplitude of any ſtarre being giuen, to finde the height of the Pole.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>VVOrke by the * as by the ☉ in the 13 Propoſition. Example: <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cturus</hi> amplitude being giuen, 37 degrees; the Pole of heauen is found to be 52 degr. aboue the Horizon eleuated.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="proposition">
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:13868:16"/>
                  <head>Propoſition 8. <hi>To finde the right Aſcention of any ſtarre.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>VVOrke by the ſtarre, as by the Sun in the 14 Prop. Example: Bring <hi>Arcturus</hi> to the Meridian, and the point in the equinoctiall being then vnder the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridian, ſheweth the right Aſcention to be 209 degrees.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="proposition">
                  <head>Propoſition 9. <hi>To find the crooked Aſcention of any ſtarre.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>VVOrke by the ſtarre, as you did by the Sunne in the 15 Propoſition. Example: The place of <hi>Arcturus</hi> being brought to the Horizon, the degrees of the equinoctiall againſt the Horizon, doe proue his crooked Aſcention to be 178 degrees.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="proposition">
                  <head>Propoſition 10. <hi>To finde the Latitude of any ſtarre.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>PVt the center of the Quadrant of Alti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, being taken from the Meridian,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:13868:16"/>
vpon the pole of the eclipticke, <hi>viz. Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cturus</hi> Latitude is to be meaſured from the pole eclipticke with the Quadrant of alti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, and is found to be 31 degr. 30 min. and his Longitude is in 19 degrees of ♎, to be reckoned with the quadrant of alti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, being brought from the pole eclip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke, to the eclipticke or zodiack, paſſing right on the place of <hi>Arcturus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Compoſtella</hi> in <hi>Galicia</hi> is by ſundrie mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters found to bee in the 43 parallel, which is in Latitude 43 degrees Northward, and in the 11 meridian 30 minutes, which is in Longitude 11 degr. ½.</p>
                  <list>
                     <head>Circles of</head>
                     <item>Latitude or Altitude, beginneth from the equinoctiall by pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallels Northward or South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, to bee reckoned to 90 degrees.</item>
                     <item>Longitude to bee reckoned by Meridians numbred in the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinoctiall, which is that me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridian paſſing betweene the equinoctial and the Iles of the Canaries, &amp; are numbred into the Eaſt round about y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> globe, <hi>viz.</hi> to 360 degrees.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="36" facs="tcp:13868:17"/>
One houre containeth 15 degrees or 60 minutes, and 4 of thoſe minutes containe one degree: therefore diuiding ſtill your number of minutes by 4, and the quotient ſhall be degrees.</p>
                  <div type="example">
                     <head>Example.</head>
                     <p>Twelue minutes of an houre giue three degrees of Longitude, which is 12 min. ſo that euery minute of an houres time is ¼ part of one degree in Longitude, as is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by the worke following.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="proposition">
                  <head>Here followeth the 11 Propoſition con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Starres.</head>
                  <head type="sub">
                     <hi>Two ſtarres ſeene in the Horizon to riſe or to ſet at one time, thereby to finde the height of the Pole.</hi> Example.</head>
                  <p>THe two ſtarres riſing together, the one is the firſt ſtarre in <hi>Orions girdle,</hi> and the other * is that which is in <hi>Pegaſus</hi> noſe: therefore turne the Globe vntill you fit the ſaid two ſtarres equall with the Horizon in the Eaſt: then ſhall the portion, betwixt the North pole and that Horizon, teach you the poles height to be in 53. degrees.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="proposition">
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:13868:17"/>
                  <head>Propoſition 12. <hi>The place of the</hi> ☉ <hi>and the length of the day being giuen, to finde the height of the Pole.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THe place of the ☉ giuen is in 17 degr. of ♎, and the length of the day giuen, is 11 houres. Therefore firſt finde out the right aſcention of the ☉, then number fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that place ſo many meridians, as doe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the halfe length of the day giuen, and let the end of thoſe degrees reſt vnder the fixed meridian: then moue the meridian of the Globe, vntill you fit the place of the ☉ in the Horizon, and then ſhall you finde vpon the meridian the iuſt height of the Pole. For example.</p>
                  <p>The ☉ being in 17. degrees of ♎, her right aſcention is found to be 195 degrees, the daies length giuen is 11: therfore take the one halfe, that is 5 houres ½: which time reduced into degrees, <hi>facit</hi> 82 degrees 30 min. the which ſubtracted out of the ☉ aſcention 195, there reſt 112 degr. 30 min. which number finde out vpon the equino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctial, and bring it to the fixed meridian, and there keepe the ſame, vntill by mouing the meridian you do bring the 17 degree of ♎ equall with the Horizon: that done, then
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:13868:18"/>
will the height of the Pole be found eleua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted iuſt 51 degrees.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="proposition">
                  <head>Propoſition 13. <hi>The length of the day and amplitude of the ☉ being giuen, to finde the height of the Pole, and the ☉ declination.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THe length of the day giuen, is eleuen houres. The amplitude of the ☉ gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, is 10 degrees. Therfore number from the firſt meridian Weſtward, thoſe degrees that haue the length of the giuen day, redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in degrees doe yeeld, and let the end of thoſe degrees begin in the equinoctiall reſt vnder the fixed meridian: then moue the globe vntill you haue fitted y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt meridian to cut in the amplitude giuen, and then ſhal the meridian of the Globe ſhew the iuſt height of the Pole. Example.</p>
                  <p>The length of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> day giuen, is 11 houres, whoſe halfe is 5½, the ſame reduced into de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, <hi>facit</hi> 28 degr. 30 min. the which ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken out of 360 degrees, reſt 277 degr. 30 min. the latter point whereof fixe vnder the fixed meridian, there holding the ſame, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till by mouing of the fixed meridian, you can bring the giuen amplitude on the Eaſt
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:13868:18"/>
ſide to fit vpon the firſt point of the meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian: which done, then ſhall you finde the Pole eleuated 51 degrees aboue the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizon.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>PROPOSITIONS THAT ARE reſolued vpon the Terreſtriall Globe. <hi>That all Propoſitions concerning the ☉, may as well be reſolued vpon the Terreſtriall as the Celeſtiall Globe.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="1" type="proposition">
                  <head>Propoſition 1. <hi>To finde the Latitude of any place.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>BRing the place, whoſe Latitude is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, to the meridian of the Globe, and the portion of the meridian included betweene that place and the equinoctiall, ſheweth the Latitude.</p>
                  <list>
                     <head>And ſo are the following places in La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude Northward.</head>
                     <item>London 51.<hi>
                           <hi rend="sup">d</hi>.</hi> 30. <hi>m.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Hamborough. 54.</item>
                     <item>Amſterdam 52. <hi>full.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Antwerpe. 51. <hi>ſcarce.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Bolloigne. 48. 30.</item>
                     <item>Paris. 48. 30.</item>
                     <item>
                        <pb n="40" facs="tcp:13868:19"/>
Lyons. 46.</item>
                     <item>Bordeaux. 43. 40.</item>
                     <item>S. Ander. 42. 30.</item>
                     <item>The Groyne. 43.</item>
                     <item>Liſborne. 39. 30.</item>
                     <item>Seuill. 37. 30.</item>
                     <item>Cape-Martin 39. 40.</item>
                     <item>Genoa. 45.</item>
                     <item>Roma. 42.</item>
                     <item>Naples. 41</item>
                     <item>Palermo. 37. 30.</item>
                     <item>Venice. 46.</item>
                     <item>Raguſi. 42.</item>
                     <item>Ciprus. 37. 15.</item>
                     <item>Rhodus, 38.</item>
                     <item>Ieruſalem. 34. 40.</item>
                     <item>Teneriffe. 28. 30.</item>
                     <item>Capo-blanco. 20.</item>
                     <item>Iſla S. Helena. 16. 40. <hi>Southward.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Nombre de dios. 9. <hi>Northward.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Panama. 8.</item>
                     <item>Capodeuela. 10.</item>
                     <item>Hauana. 22.</item>
                     <item>San Domingo. 17. 30.</item>
                     <item>Iſle Icaris. 66.</item>
                     <item>Fane Inſul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 64. 30.</item>
                     <item>Iſlandie. 67. 30.</item>
                     <item>Gibraltare. 35.</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="proposition">
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:13868:19"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Propoſition</hi> 2. To finde the Longitude of any place.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>BRing the place appointed to the meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian of the Globe, and the degrees cut by the meridian in the equinoctiall, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Longitude.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And ſo are the places here vnder found in longitude,</hi> viz.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>London. 20. 30. longitude.</item>
                     <item>Hamborough. 33. 30.</item>
                     <item>Antwerpe 26. 30.</item>
                     <item>Paris. 24.</item>
                     <item>Bordeaux. 22.</item>
                     <item>S. Ander. 18. 30.</item>
                     <item>The Groyne. 13.</item>
                     <item>Liſbona. 13.</item>
                     <item>Seuill. 17. degrees.</item>
                     <item>Genoa. 35.</item>
                     <item>Roma. 37.</item>
                     <item>Venice. 40.</item>
                     <item>Palermo. 37. 30.</item>
                     <item>Ieruſalem. 69.</item>
                     <item>San Domingo in the Weſt Indies. 310.</item>
                     <item>Teneriffe. 3. degr. 30.</item>
                     <item>Palona. 1. degr. longitude.</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="proposition">
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:13868:20"/>
                  <head>Propoſition 3. <hi>To finde the difference betweene any two pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces vpon the Globe.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>TAke the diſtance with a paire of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes, and apply the ſame to the equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noctiall, accounting for euery degree 60 miles, or 20 leagues, or according to that countrey wherein you are.</p>
                  <p>And ſo are the diſtances betweene</p>
                  <list>
                     <head>
                        <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> and</head>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> 39. <hi>facit</hi> 795. <hi>leagues.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Antwerpe</hi> 3. 30. <hi>facit</hi> 70.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Paris.</hi> 4. 20. <hi>facit</hi> 86. ⅔.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Venice</hi> 13. 40. <hi>facit</hi> 273. ⅓.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Bordeaux</hi> 8. 00. <hi>facit</hi> 170.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Liſbona</hi> 13. ⅔. <hi>facit</hi> 273.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Seuill</hi> 14. ¾. <hi>facit</hi> 295.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Roma</hi> 16. ½. <hi>facit</hi> 330 <hi>leagues.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Teneriffe</hi> 27. 00. <hi>facit</hi> 540.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Terra noua</hi> 28. 00. <hi>facit</hi> 560.</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="proposition">
                  <head>Propoſition 4. <hi>The Latitude and Longitude of any place be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing giuen, to finde the ſame vpon the Globe.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>BRing the Latitude of that place to the Meridian of the Globe, and vnder
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:13868:20"/>
the Meridian in the Latitude, ſhall the place required be found.</p>
                  <p>By the firſt and ſecond Propoſition is this Propoſition reſolued.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="proposition">
                  <head>Propoſition 5. <hi>To finde the Antipodes to any place.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>BRing the place appointed to the Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian, and note the Latitude: then in the oppoſite degree of Latitude vnder the Meridian, you ſhall finde the point of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>podes.</p>
                  <p>And after this ſort are thoſe Antipodes to <hi>London,</hi> that dwell 51 degrees ½ Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, and in 198 degrees Longitude in the South-maine.</p>
                  <p>And to <hi>Seuill,</hi> thoſe that dwell in 37 de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, 30 min. Latitude, and 196 degr. Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitude, are Antipodes.</p>
                  <p>And to <hi>Liſbone,</hi> thoſe that dwell in 39 degr. 30 min. Latitude, and 192 deg. ½ Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitude, are Antipodes.</p>
                  <p>And to <hi>Antwerpe,</hi> thoſe that dwell in 51 degr. Latitude, and 195 deg. Longitude in the ſaid South-maine.</p>
                  <p>The people dwelling vnder the North and South pole, and vnder the Eclipticke
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:13868:21"/>
poles, are Antipodes the one to the other.</p>
                  <p>Thoſe of <hi>Cuſco</hi> in <hi>America,</hi> are Antipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des to thoſe of <hi>Narſinga</hi> in <hi>Eaſt India.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thoſe of <hi>Lyma</hi> and <hi>Calicut,</hi> are Antipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des to each other.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Inſulanes</hi> of <hi>Serrana</hi> and <hi>Iona,</hi> are Antipodes to each other.</p>
                  <p>Thoſe of <hi>Xaliſco, Colinia, Guatatlan, Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tratlan, Guaxaca,</hi> &amp;c. are Antipodes, to the <hi>Inſulanes</hi> of S. <hi>Laurence.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thoſe of <hi>Malaca</hi> are Antipodes to that people dwelling in the prouince of <hi>Oma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gua.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="proposition">
                  <head>Propoſition 6. <hi>To finde the difference of time betweene any two places.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>BRing the Eaſtermoſt place to the Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian, and rectifie the Index: then bring the ſecond place alſo to the Meridian, and marke where the Index cuts, it ſheweth the houre at that ſecond place, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is noone at the firſt. Or to doe this more preciſely, finde the difference of the Longitude be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt theſe two places: which remainder reduce into time, by allowing 15 degr. for an houre, and the difference is found.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="proposition">
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:13868:21"/>
                  <head>Propoſition 7. <hi>To finde the difference of the longeſt day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene any two places.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>FInde the length of the day at each place, by the Propoſition before taught, and the difference betweene them is found by their ſeuerall lengths.</p>
                  <p>Firſt it is to be noted, in Northen Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude the longeſt day of the yeare is, when the ☉ is in the firſt point of ♋, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore according to that place is the longeſt daies of ſeueral places here vnder ſet down, the which preciſely haue been calculated, by the difference of Aſcention, that the ☉ made at one ſame time in ſeuerall places.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>London</hi> lying in the Latitude of 51 deg. 30 m. and the place of the ☉ taken in the firſt degree of ♋, had right Aſcention 90 degrees, and crooked Aſcention 58 degr.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Liſbona</hi> Latitude 39. 30, makes 10 degr. difference of Aſcention: which doubled, <hi>facit</hi> 40 degr. thoſe reduced into time, <hi>facit</hi> 2 houres 40 min. thoſe added to 12, <hi>facit</hi> 14 houres, 40 min. for the longeſt day.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Genoa</hi> Latitude 45 degrees, the ☉ right Aſcention is 90 degrees, the crooked 68,
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                        <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="48" facs="tcp:13868:22"/>
is alwaies of 12 houres long, but winter or ſommer the ☉ declineth North or South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Capo de vela</hi> in the Weſt Indies in 12 de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of Latitude, at the ſame time when the ☉ is in the firſt degree of ♋, hath 90 degrees right Aſcention, and crooked 85 diff. is 5, which doubled is 10 min. which reduced make 40 min. of time, which ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to 12 houres, ſheweth their longeſt day to be 12 houres, 40 min.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hauana</hi> at the ſame time differeth the ☉ in Aſcention 9 degr. 30 minutes, double makes 19, which is time one houre, 16 min. which added to 12, maketh 13 houres, 16 min. for their longeſt day.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>San Domingo</hi> Iland maketh the ☉ 7 de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees ½ for difference of Aſcention: which doubled, maketh 15: is one houre time, ſo is their longeſt day 13 houres.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Faire Iland</hi> in 64 deg. of Latitude the ☉ hath at the ſame time 90 deg. right Aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, crooked 30, reſt 60 for difference thereof, which doubled, <hi>facit</hi> 120 degrees, which maketh time 8 houres, thoſe added to 12 houres, ſheweth that the longeſt day there is 20 houres.</p>
                  <p>At <hi>Icaria</hi> Iland in 66 degrees Latitude,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:13868:22"/>
the ☉ being in the firſt degree of ♋, hath 90 degr. right Aſcentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, crooked 20, which difference is 70: thoſe doubled, maketh 140 degr. which is 9 houres, 20 m. of time, ſo is their longeſt day of the yeere 21 <hi rend="sup">h</hi>. 20 minutes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Iſland</hi> in 67 degr. Latitude on the ſame time hath crooked Aſcention 8 deg. which taken from 90, differeth 82 degrees, which doubled, are 164 degr. which reduced into time, doe giue 10 houres, 56 min. and thoſe added to the equinoctiall day, <hi>facit</hi> 22 <hi rend="sup">h</hi>. 56 min. for the longeſt day in the yeere.</p>
                  <p>Theſe differences of Aſcention is more preciſely found by proiecting the figures, and then by ſcale and Compaſſe, and yet more preciſely by Arithmeticall calcula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by which the ſaid difference and length of daies are found.</p>
                  <p>14 <hi rend="sup">h</hi>. 20. min. <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi> 17. 30.</p>
                  <p>13. 48 <hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 56 min. <hi>Teneriffe.</hi> 13. 37.</p>
                  <p>13. 12 <hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 56 min. <hi>Capo-blanco.</hi> 9. 7.</p>
                  <p>12. 32. <hi>Nombre de dios.</hi> 4.</p>
                  <p>12. 28. <hi>Panama.</hi> 3. 30.</p>
                  <p>12.<hi>—San Thome</hi> being vnder the equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noctial, the ☉ maketh no difference, and therefore alwaies 12 houres.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="50" facs="tcp:13868:23"/>
12. 42.<hi>—Capo de vela</hi> 5. 15.</p>
                  <p>13. 20. 48. m. <hi>Hauana.</hi> 10. 6.</p>
                  <p>13. 3. 4 m. <hi>San Domingo.</hi> 7. 53.</p>
                  <p>20. 44. 40 m. <hi>Fane Inſula.</hi> 65. 35.</p>
                  <p>22. 9. 20 m. <hi>Icari Inſula.</hi> 76. 10.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="proposition">
                  <head>Propoſition 8. <hi>To finde the Horizontall poſition and diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwixt any two places.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>FIrſt rectifie the Globe for that place, from the which you would know the Horizontall poſition and diſtance to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place: bring alſo that firſt place to the Meridian of the Globe, then put the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drant of Altitude on the Zenith, there let the Globe reſt, then bring the quadrant of Altitude ouer the two places, and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees cut by the end of the quadrant in the Horizon, ſheweth the Horizontall poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the degree cut by the ſecond place in the quadrant, account from the Center downwards, ſheweth the diſtance.</p>
                  <div type="example">
                     <head>For example.</head>
                     <p>The bearing of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> to <hi>London</hi> is 50 degr. accounted from the North point Weſtward, and the diſtance is 38 degr. 30
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:13868:23"/>
minutes. And from <hi>London</hi> to <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> the bearing is 85 degrees, accounting from the South point Eaſtward, and the diſtance is as before.</p>
                     <p>Now to finde the Rhombe, adde the two Horizontall poſitions together, and the one halfe thereof ſheweth it.</p>
                     <p>From <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> to <hi>Aleppo,</hi> the bearing is 69 degrees from the North point Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, the diſtance is 43 degr. ½: and <hi>Alep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po</hi> beareth to <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> 77 degrees from the North point Eaſtward.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> to <hi>Teneriffe</hi> beareth 77 degr. from the North point Weſtward; and <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neriffe</hi> to <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> 64 degrees, accounting from the North point Eaſtwards; and the diſtance betwixt the two places is 55 de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees ½.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> to <hi>Rome</hi> beareth 67 degr. from the North point Weſtward, diſtance 24. ½: <hi>Rome</hi> to <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> 86 degr. from the South point Weſtward.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> to <hi>Gibraltare</hi> beareth 76 degr. from the North point Weſtward, and the diſtance is 43 degr. and <hi>Gibraltare</hi> to <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> beareth 73 degrees from the North point Eaſtward.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:13868:24"/>
               <head>OF THE WORLD.</head>
               <p>THe world is diuided into two parts, <hi>viz.</hi> Elementall, and Etheriall parts.</p>
               <p>The firſt is ſubiect to daily alterations, and containeth foure Elements: that is, the Earth, the Water, the Aire, and the Fire.</p>
               <p>An element is that, whereof any thing is compounded, and of it ſelfe not compoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; of theſe foure eleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, any part of any kinde is named for the whole, as any part of the earth is called the earth.</p>
               <p>The Etheriall parts doth compaſſe the elementall parts in the concauitie thereof, and containeth 10 Spheres: whereof the firſt is the ſphere of the <hi>Moone,</hi> and is next vnto vs. The ſecond is <hi>Mercurius:</hi> the third <hi>Venus:</hi> the fourth <hi>Sol:</hi> the fifth <hi>Mars:</hi> the ſixth, <hi>Iupiter:</hi> the ſeuenth, <hi>Saturnus:</hi> the eighth ſphere is the ſtarrie firmament: the ninth is the Chriſtaline heauen: The tenth, <hi>Primum mobile,</hi> which doth containe all the reſt within it, and whatſoeuer is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:13868:24"/>
or aboue that, is the habitation of God and his Angels.</p>
               <p>The reaſon how theſe ſpheres were firſt found out, were their contrarie motions in the heauens, obſerued by the ancient lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Aſtronomers, and we finde that by our owne obſeruations, as thus, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, all things in the heauens turne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the earth, vpon the poles of heauen in foure and twentie houres, and theſe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are from the Eaſt into the Weſt, and this wee attribute to the motion of the 10 ſphere, or <hi>Primum mobile,</hi> without ſtaying, being ſo appointed by God fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and carrieth about with him in vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence all the other ſpheres.</p>
               <p>All the reſt of the ſpheres haue contrarie motions, euery one in his kinde, though farre ſlower then the other, and their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions is contrary from the Weſt to the Eaſt, and ſo are carried about often times by the firſt mouer, before they make one perfect reuolution in themſelues.</p>
               <p>The Chriſtaline or ninth ſphere his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is almoſt vnſenſible, and is called the trembling motion, and is performed, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>Ptolomie</hi> his opinion, in 36000 yeeres, but by the opinion of others in a
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:13868:25"/>
farre longer time, as in 49000. yeeres.</p>
               <p>The eighth ſphere, being the ſtarrie fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mament, performeth his motion in 7000 yeeres.</p>
               <p>The reſt of the ſpheres are the ſeuen Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets, each ſphere containeth in it but one ſtarre, whereof the vppermoſt and ſloweſt is <hi>Saturne,</hi> which performeth his courſe in 24 yeeres, 162 daies, and 12 houres.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iupiter</hi> performeth in 11. yeeres, 133 daies, and 23 houres.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mars</hi> performeth in 322 daies, and 23 houres.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sol</hi> performeth in 365 daies &amp; 6 houres, which is one whole yeere.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Venus</hi> in 385 daies, 9 houres, performeth her courſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mercurie</hi> performeth as the ☉ in 365 daies, and 6 houres.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Luna</hi> performeth her courſe once euerie 27 daies, and 12 houres.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:13868:25"/>
               <head>THE CHARACTERS OF THE Planets are theſe following.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Saturne</hi> ♄ <hi>Mars</hi> ♂ <hi>Venus</hi> ♀ <hi>Iupiter</hi> ♃ <hi>Sol</hi> ☉ <hi>Mercurie</hi> ☿ <hi>Luna</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>
               </p>
               <p>THere are points mouable in the Eclip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke, which are called the Dragons head, and the Dragons taile, and their ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters are theſe: Dragons head ☋, Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons taile ☊.</p>
               <p>The Dragons head is the point in the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipticke, which the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> toucheth, when ſhe croſſeth the Eclipticke, and paſſeth to the Northwards of it.</p>
               <p>The ☊ is the point in the Eclipticke, where the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> paſſeth by, when ſhe croſſeth the Ecliptick, &amp; paſſeth by it to the South, and theſe two points are oppoſite the one to the other.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:13868:26"/>
                  <head>To know how the Planets reigne euery houre of the day, and night: beginning with Saturday.</head>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <head>Houres of the day.</head>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>1.</cell>
                           <cell>2.</cell>
                           <cell>3.</cell>
                           <cell>4.</cell>
                           <cell>5.</cell>
                           <cell>6.</cell>
                           <cell>7.</cell>
                           <cell>8.</cell>
                           <cell>9.</cell>
                           <cell>10.</cell>
                           <cell>11.</cell>
                           <cell>12.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Sat.</cell>
                           <cell>♄.</cell>
                           <cell>♃.</cell>
                           <cell>♂.</cell>
                           <cell>☉.</cell>
                           <cell>♀.</cell>
                           <cell>☿.</cell>
                           <cell>☽.</cell>
                           <cell>♄.</cell>
                           <cell>♃.</cell>
                           <cell>♂.</cell>
                           <cell>☉.</cell>
                           <cell>♀.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>☉.</cell>
                           <cell>♀.</cell>
                           <cell>☿.</cell>
                           <cell>☽.</cell>
                           <cell>♄.</cell>
                           <cell>♃.</cell>
                           <cell>♂.</cell>
                           <cell>☉.</cell>
                           <cell>♀.</cell>
                           <cell>☿.</cell>
                           <cell>☽.</cell>
                           <cell>♄.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>☽.</cell>
                           <cell>♄.</cell>
                           <cell>♃.</cell>
                           <cell>♂.</cell>
                           <cell>☉.</cell>
                           <cell>♀.</cell>
                           <cell>☿.</cell>
                           <cell>☽.</cell>
                           <cell>♄.</cell>
                           <cell>♃.</cell>
                           <cell>♂.</cell>
                           <cell>☉.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>♂.</cell>
                           <cell>☉.</cell>
                           <cell>♀.</cell>
                           <cell>☿.</cell>
                           <cell>☽.</cell>
                           <cell>♄.</cell>
                           <cell>♃.</cell>
                           <cell>♂.</cell>
                           <cell>☉.</cell>
                           <cell>♀.</cell>
                           <cell>☿.</cell>
                           <cell>☽.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>☿.</cell>
                           <cell>☽.</cell>
                           <cell>♄.</cell>
                           <cell>♃.</cell>
                           <cell>♂.</cell>
                           <cell>☉.</cell>
                           <cell>♀.</cell>
                           <cell>☿.</cell>
                           <cell>☽.</cell>
                           <cell>♄.</cell>
                           <cell>♃.</cell>
                           <cell>♂.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>♃.</cell>
                           <cell>♂.</cell>
                           <cell>☉.</cell>
                           <cell>♀.</cell>
                           <cell>☿.</cell>
                           <cell>☽.</cell>
                           <cell>♄.</cell>
                           <cell>♃.</cell>
                           <cell>♂.</cell>
                           <cell>☉.</cell>
                           <cell>♀.</cell>
                           <cell>☿.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>♀.</cell>
                           <cell>☿.</cell>
                           <cell>☽.</cell>
                           <cell>♄.</cell>
                           <cell>♃.</cell>
                           <cell>♂.</cell>
                           <cell>☉.</cell>
                           <cell>♀.</cell>
                           <cell>☿.</cell>
                           <cell>☽.</cell>
                           <cell>♄.</cell>
                           <cell>♃.</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <head>Houres of the night.</head>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>1.</cell>
                           <cell>2.</cell>
                           <cell>3.</cell>
                           <cell>4.</cell>
                           <cell>5.</cell>
                           <cell>6.</cell>
                           <cell>7.</cell>
                           <cell>8.</cell>
                           <cell>9.</cell>
                           <cell>10.</cell>
                           <cell>11.</cell>
                           <cell>12.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Sat.</cell>
                           <cell>☿</cell>
                           <cell>☾</cell>
                           <cell>♄</cell>
                           <cell>♃</cell>
                           <cell>♂</cell>
                           <cell>☉</cell>
                           <cell>♀</cell>
                           <cell>☿</cell>
                           <cell>☾</cell>
                           <cell>♄</cell>
                           <cell>♃</cell>
                           <cell>♂</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>♃</cell>
                           <cell>♂</cell>
                           <cell>☉</cell>
                           <cell>♀</cell>
                           <cell>☿</cell>
                           <cell>☾</cell>
                           <cell>♄</cell>
                           <cell>♃</cell>
                           <cell>♂</cell>
                           <cell>☉</cell>
                           <cell>♀</cell>
                           <cell>☿</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>♀</cell>
                           <cell>☿</cell>
                           <cell>☾</cell>
                           <cell>♄</cell>
                           <cell>♃</cell>
                           <cell>♂</cell>
                           <cell>☉</cell>
                           <cell>♀</cell>
                           <cell>☿</cell>
                           <cell>☾</cell>
                           <cell>♄</cell>
                           <cell>♃</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>♄</cell>
                           <cell>♃</cell>
                           <cell>♂</cell>
                           <cell>☉</cell>
                           <cell>♀</cell>
                           <cell>☿</cell>
                           <cell>☾</cell>
                           <cell>♄</cell>
                           <cell>♃</cell>
                           <cell>♂</cell>
                           <cell>☉</cell>
                           <cell>♀</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>☉</cell>
                           <cell>♀</cell>
                           <cell>☿</cell>
                           <cell>☾</cell>
                           <cell>♄</cell>
                           <cell>♃</cell>
                           <cell>♂</cell>
                           <cell>☉</cell>
                           <cell>♀</cell>
                           <cell>☿</cell>
                           <cell>☾</cell>
                           <cell>♄</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>☾</cell>
                           <cell>♄</cell>
                           <cell>♃</cell>
                           <cell>♂</cell>
                           <cell>☉</cell>
                           <cell>♀</cell>
                           <cell>☿</cell>
                           <cell>☾</cell>
                           <cell>♄</cell>
                           <cell>♃</cell>
                           <cell>♂</cell>
                           <cell>☉</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>♂</cell>
                           <cell>☉</cell>
                           <cell>♀</cell>
                           <cell>☿</cell>
                           <cell>☾</cell>
                           <cell>♄</cell>
                           <cell>♃</cell>
                           <cell>♂</cell>
                           <cell>☉</cell>
                           <cell>♀</cell>
                           <cell>☿</cell>
                           <cell>☾</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:13868:26"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
